<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Reflexions upon a late pamphlet, intituled, A narrative written by E. Settle with a vindication of the proceedings of the nation from aspersions cast upon them by that libel.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 103KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A58372</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12241304</idno>
  <idno type="VID">56781</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240940060</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing R716</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R780</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12241304</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A58372)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56781)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 875:50)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Reflexions upon a late pamphlet, intituled, A narrative written by E. Settle with a vindication of the proceedings of the nation from aspersions cast upon them by that libel.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 20 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.H. for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Settle, Elkanah, 1648-1724. --  Narrative.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Popish Plot, 1678.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56781:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56781:1"/>
            <p>REFLEXIONS Upon a late PAMPHLET, INTITULED, A NARRATIVE Written by <hi>E. SETTLE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>WITH A VINDICATION OF THE Proceedings of the NATION from the Asper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions cast upon them by that Libel.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Nam te Cur aliquis Sciat fuisse?</l>
               <l>Ignotus Pereas, Miser, Necesse est.</l>
               <l>Non deerunt tamen hac in Ʋrbe forsan</l>
               <l>Ʋnus, vel duo, tresve, quatuorve;</l>
               <l>Pellem rodere qui velint caninam.</l>
               <l>Nos hac à Scabie tenemus Ʋngues.</l>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. H.</hi> for the Author. 1683.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:56781:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56781:2"/>
            <head>REFLEXIONS Upon a late PAMPHLET, INTITULED, A NARRATIVE Written by <hi>E. SETTLE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>I Thought my self bound, both by the Duty of an <hi>Englishman,</hi> of a loyal Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and a true <hi>Protestant,</hi> to vindicate the Justice of the Nation from the Aspersions cast upon it by a late Libel, called a <hi>Narrative</hi> written by <hi>E. Settle,</hi> which I have read over with some Attention, and have found it to be a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium and Collection of the several <hi>Popish</hi> Pamphlets which stole abroad since the Discovery of the Plot, with intent to ridicule it, frame imaginary Incoheren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, and throw it upon the <hi>Protestants.</hi> Out of those Libels it is the Author has made a shift to patch up a Narrative, and proclaim himself a Villain: He long since was said to aspire to the honour of being the City Poet; but now his Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion puts him upon Affairs of State, and undoubtedly this Essay of his is to shew how well capacitated he is for an Imployment in a Catholick Design. To speak plainly, I see he puts in to be Secretary to the <hi>Jesuits</hi> in <hi>Newgate;</hi> and truly eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Action of his, as well as his own Confession, speak him to be Traytor enough as to deserve the place: for my part, I'll assure him of my Vote; and now <hi>Nath. Thompson</hi> may chear up, and promise <hi>himself</hi> some Gains after all his Losses, seeing he cannot want work since <hi>Elkanah</hi> will copy Treason as fast as e're the <hi>Jesuits</hi> Brains can spawn it. A Dedication to a Pope <hi>Joan</hi> or <hi>a Fairy Queen</hi> at a <hi>Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew</hi> Fair, bring in but rare and uncertain Profit; but an Imployment of this nature is sure to be attended with a rich and constant Revenue. He is said to have threatned to declare to the World what Gifts and Encouragements he has recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from the <hi>Whiggish</hi> Party for the promoting of Treason. But I perceive by his omitting of it in this occasion, that he thinks to stay, and see how far his new Patrons will exceed the <hi>Whiggs</hi> in their Bounties; and then having ballanced the Account, I suppose we may expect to see the Particulars, tho I do not question but his new Masters will prove by much the most liberal and generous Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors in all things that tend towards a Conspiracy. But I shall, according to their Desires, proceed to the giving you a Catalogue of those Remarks and Reflexions which I have made upon this Pamphlet: And for that purpose, I shall begin with his Epistle, wherein he owns himself the greatest Villain that perhaps has been up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Earth. He says, That the Duke, <hi>upon condescending to hear his Servants, in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a very humble Cause that was depending between his</hi> Royal Highness's <hi>Servants and him</hi> Elkanah, <hi>did nothing but the highest piece of Justice in giving it against him; yet that his defeated Vanity begat in him such a malignant Gall and Resentment, that
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56781:3"/> above seven Years would not remove; but that the License of the Press, and the Erup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the late accursed Plot, had furnish'd him with the Opportunity, under the Ʋm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage of a popular Champion, to wreak his own <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rivate Spight and Revenge, with ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumulated Wrongs, upon a Prince of such Honour and Vertue.</hi> Now the Case de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending, was, as I am credibly informed, as followeth: The <hi>Duke</hi>'s House allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> fifty Pounds a Year upon Condition they might have the Acting of all the Plays he made. But he expecting a greater third day, if acted by the King's Servants, notwithstanding his Pension, put his Play into their Hands: but his Royal Highness having done the Parties Justice, <hi>this misleed him into so much Spleen and Venome</hi> as he now pretends to recant, <hi>repent, and be asham'd of.</hi> Now pray you observe the Villany of this Fellow, who for the Vanity of having his Play Acted by a <hi>Company</hi> then most in Repute, and for the lucre of perhaps a Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney or two which he might have expected more from that House than the other, he not only broke his Covenants with his Royal Highness's Servants, but upon his Disappointment, prosecuted his Royal Highness himself with all the Rancor that could swell the Heart of the most bitter and most hellish Traitor, and cared not tho he involved three Kingdoms in the ruine of that Prince, so he could but glut and satiate his Revenge. Now indeed I have heard of a <hi>Ravillac,</hi> of a <hi>Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus,</hi> of a <hi>Faux;</hi> but either the Sufferings of their Country, or their own, Biggotry, with the devilish Infusions and Insinuations of their Priests, prevailed with, prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and blindly hurried them to their hellish Attempts and Undertakings: But aspiring <hi>Elkanah</hi> being resolved to have the first place in the rank of Infamy, scorn'd to copy others by making Religion and the Interest of his Country the motives of his Actions, but undertook to rival even the Devil himself, by pursuing, with all the <hi>Spight and Hatred</hi> imaginable, only for his private Revenge, the Ruine of a Prince whom he declares stands possess'd of the highest Honour and Virtue. But pray you see in what Colours the Honour and Virtue of this Prince be drawn, in the Author of the first Part of the <hi>Character of a Popish Successor,</hi> page 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And all this his Glory shall do, his Glory, the Glory of a Papist; a pretty airy Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, how shall we ever expect that Glory will steer the Actions of a</hi> Popish <hi>Successor, when there is not that thing so abject which he shall refuse to do, or that Shape or Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrisie so scandalous he shall not assume when</hi> Rome <hi>or</hi> Rome<hi>'s Interest shall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand; nay, when his own petulant Stubbornness shall but sway him? As for example, for one fit he shall come to the Protestant Church and be a Member of their Communion, notwithstanding at the same time his Face belies his Heart, and in his Soul he is a</hi> Romanist; <hi>nay, he shall vary his Disguises as often as an</hi> Algerine <hi>his Colours, and change his Flag to conceal the Pyrate. As for instance, another fit, for whole Years to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, he shall come neither to one Church nor th' other, and participate of neither Communion till ignobly he plays the unprincely, nay, the unmanly Hypocrite, so long that he shelters himself under the face of an</hi> Atheist <hi>to shrowd a</hi> Papist, <hi>a Visor more fit for a</hi> Banditto <hi>than a</hi> Prince. <hi>And this methinks is so wretched and so despicable a Disguise, that it looks like being ashamed of his God.</hi> But this you'll say was said when he was in his Spleen: but now that he thinks he has told him his own, and satisfied his Resentment, he begs Pardon, acknowledges his Errors, and repents: but give me leave to ask from whence this Humiliation and Repentance proceeds; When those Words were written by Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> who has own'd himself the Author of 'em, did not that sad Juncture threaten the Nation with a direful Revolution; and what he now wonderfully masks under his private Resentments and Revenge, was it not making his Court to a Party whom he considered as the mony'd part of the Nation, and ready inclin'd to reward and succour all those who had Suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency and Probity: but now that the Tide is turned, that all the Efforts of zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Patriots for the settling the Peace and procuring the Happiness of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try have been diverted, that he has lost his <hi>powerful Champion,</hi> under whose <hi>Ʋm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brage</hi> and <hi>Influence</hi> he meant to combat, and that an Inundation of <hi>Torisme</hi> seems to threaten the whole Land, is it not to be suspected that his Recantation and Repentance are only to save his Bacon, and that had the same Circumstances continued, Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Revenge and Resentment would have been still alive, and as eager upon the pursuit as ever?</p>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:56781:3"/>
            <p>The Truth is, Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Resentment and Revenge was only his Interest and his Bread, as long as he had the least Prospect of receiving any benefit by being an <hi>Anti-Yorkist:</hi> he shew'd himself a zealous <hi>Partizan</hi> of the <hi>Whiggs,</hi> vainly ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping perhaps, that his new Patrons would be careful to promote so officious a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister as he endeavoured to shew himself to be; and that Ambition was the ruling Passion of his Heart, is plain from what he says in the Discovery he has made in his Epistle <hi>Dedicatory,</hi> where he retracts again what he had but just before said, and lays at the doors of some of the greatest Men in <hi>England</hi> the enormous crimes he accused himself of, saying <hi>they were to answer for his Sins.</hi> But then again to insinuate how he went Jig by Jole with those great Men, and to hint how that the World may one day expect to see him put in for an Evidences place; nay, to let you know how that he looked upon himself as a <hi>Patriot</hi> in those days, he tells you, That <hi>where the true Preservation of the Protestant Religion makes one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triot (as they call themselves) Ʋneasiness, Disgust, or a Court-grudge, makes twenty, whilst Reformation is the least business of those who pretend most to it. How many Persons of the highest Quality in the Kingdom (if they would be half so ingenious as I am,</hi> mark that) <hi>could tell you, That tho Religion and Property are the pretended Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels against the great Pilots above, their real Grievance is, that their own Hands are not at the Rudder, and the State-Helm is only steer'd awry because that some happier, some envied Court-Darling, sits at it before them.</hi> And presently after, <hi>But now tho this plain Confession, how disadvantagious soever to my self, might have been curtail'd into a something more excusable Error by laying the whole Blame on that more pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Folly of being mistaken, or seduced. Yet I declare, I had rather treble my Blush<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es than fly to so mean a Refuge as a Lye for any part of an Apology.</hi> Poor <hi>Elkanah,</hi> I am sorry for thee: I see thou art fitter to succeed <hi>Oliver</hi>'s Porter than take up the Cudgels of an <hi>Irish</hi> Evidence, tho indeed they are almost as silly and as mad as thou; for just before he had charged his Sins to the account of some of the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Men in <hi>England,</hi> and yet now he says that it was his own mere Ambition to be at the Helm, and not any Encouragement or Advice from them. <hi>But that he had finish'd his first Libel, the</hi> Character of a <hi>Popish</hi> Successor, <hi>before it ever saw Light. But then indeed,</hi> continues he, <hi>I coveted the Approbation of my</hi> Aldersgate-street <hi>Patron, and intrusted a Friend to shew it him; who, truly, made but little Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, only he expressed his dislike of one or two Passages in it,</hi> and for Amendment, <hi>bid the Author speak more favourably of Rebellion.</hi> Now as I ever suspected Mr. <hi>Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle</hi>'s Sincerity, so I suppose every one will now, both that and his Discretion too; for how can he think to impose and make the World believe that ever the Patron he mentions should make such a blunder in Politicks, as to send this worshipful Author such a Message, a thing so contrary to the Caution and Prudence of the whole Conduct of his Life; and his Enemies after they had painted him in the worst Colours their malice could afford, could never bespatter him with any rash Word or Action, much less so egregious an one as to send a Message of this na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, especially to a Poet and a professed one too, People not much admired in this Age for gifts of Continency, Fidelity, or Probity. Besides, the greatest Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors that have ever been upon the Earth, would never own their Treason, but still varnish'd o're their Crimes with some specious Pretexts or other, and stiled their Rebellions a just Defence and a self-security against Tyranny and Arbitrary Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. And that a Man of his Patron's Circumstances and Capacity should play such a <hi>Noddy</hi>'s Prank, as to fall and promote making Panegyricks upon Rebellion, at such a time a day too when he stood so much in need of being upon his Guard in a Country where such justly severe Provisions are made against Criminals of that Nature, and when so many Enemies were abroad scouting and watching to trepan him, in such a time, when he knew that upon the least false Step of that kind the Law would be let loose upon him, and he expos'd to his utmost rigour, is, without doubt, what will never find Credit with any thinking and reasonable Man. But Narrative-<hi>Elkanah</hi>'s Impudence in offering to impose this upon the World, is unquestionably to show with what Title he may lay claim, and how well capacitated he is to succeed Mr. <hi>Eustace Cummins;</hi> tho from a Parriot to an <hi>Irish</hi> Evidence I must tell you is a considerable Fall.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:56781:4"/>
            <p>After this incredible Instance of his Patron's Indiscretion, he falls to vilifying the Proceedings of the House of Commons, ridiculing the Plot, and bespattering all those who in any wise shew'd themselves zealous to put a Stop to, and prevent the <hi>Growth</hi> of <hi>Popery.</hi> In Answer to which, I shall only need to quote himself, how poor soever an Author, and for that purpose shew him, belabouring and laying at the <hi>Tories</hi> in his Epistle before <hi>Absolom Senior</hi> or <hi>Achitophel Transpos'd,</hi> says he, <hi>I cannot forbear telling you</hi> Tories, <hi>that your grinning Satyrs against the</hi> Whiggs <hi>have this one unpardonable Fault, that the Lash is more against a</hi> David <hi>than an</hi> Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel, <hi>whilst the running down of the Plot at so extravagant a rate savours of very little less than ridiculing</hi> Majesty <hi>it self, and turning all those several Royal Speeches to the</hi> Parliament, <hi>on that subject, only into those double tongued Oracles that sounded one thing and meant another. Besides, after this unmannerly Boldness of not only branding the publick Justice of the Nation, but affronting even the Throne it self, to push the Humour a little farther you run into ten times a greater Vice (and in the same Strain too) than what you so severely inveigh against; and whilst a</hi> Popish <hi>Plot, through want of sufficient Circumstances, miscarries with you, a</hi> Protestant <hi>Plot, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Witness or Circumstances at all, go currant: Nay, you are so far now from your former Niceties and Scruples, and disputing about raising of Armies, and not one Commission found, that you can swallow the raising of a whole</hi> Protestant Army, <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out either Commission or Commission-Officer; nay, the very when, where, and how, are no part of your Consideration.</hi> And presently after he adds, in the same Epistle, That <hi>the</hi> Tories <hi>who will believe no</hi> Popish Plot, <hi>may as justly come under the Deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of Fools as they that</hi> David <hi>tells us,</hi> said in their Hearts there was no God. Now is it not an unparalell'd piece of Impudence in a Fellow to run down the <hi>Popish Plot</hi> as he does all along in his Narrative, after having cry'd it up at this rate, and with what Confidence can he say how great a Truth soever; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I wonder how it came from him, <hi>That in this Reign Law and Justice were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver stretched unless to Mercy and Indulgence, and that a too easie Forgiveness, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving pardon'd Enemies, the warm ungrateful Snakes, too near the Bosom of Majesty, and too high into Trust and Honours, has been the only fault in the Throne.</hi> Now, can there be a greater Outrage done the Nation than thus to be insulted for its Indulgence and Lenity, by one who has acknowledged himself so notorious a Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minal; nay one who gives no other marks of his Repentance than that he quitted a Party that could no longer entertain him, or at least that he no longer could get Advantage by. And then to come and dare the Throne it self with a publick Declaration of his Enormities and Transgressions, when at the same time it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest he only turn'd <hi>Gat in Pan,</hi> because he could no longer be countenanced by his pretended <hi>Patrons;</hi> who beginning to smoak the Mercinariness, Sordidness, and Treachery of the Fellow, thought it not safe to entertain Commerce any longer with Persons of his Kidney; especially in so nice, so dangerous a Juncture, when every honest Man is not secure, be he never so well upon his Guard, from such Hell-hounds, who value not whose nor how many Lives they sacrifice with their own Bodies and Souls, to the Devil, so that they get but Bread, and reap but some small Temporary Advantages. As long as there were any hopes and prospect of Maintenance and Support by bawling against Plots, Popery, and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Conspiracies, I warrant you <hi>Elkanah</hi> was as loud as the best, and as zealous a Stickler against <hi>Jesuitism,</hi> as any one soever: but when <hi>Whiggism</hi> and <hi>Protestantism</hi> began to be even a barrener Soil than <hi>Parnassus,</hi> when all Evidence and Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings against Popery began to be discredited, and that the Papists began to appear again in such Shoals that the Crafty <hi>Trimmers</hi> of the Party thought it no longer Prudence to oppose the Torrent, then Sir <hi>Politick Elkanah</hi> thought fit to wheel about; and least the reality of the Conversion of this new Proselite should be brought into Question, he drew his Pen against that very Cause which he had as stiffly, nay, more vigorously defended.</p>
            <p>And, to shew that Interest is the main Spring of this Man's Affections, that he hates and loves only according to it's Dictates, that he squares Mens Virtues and Vices according to its Measures, and can be fond of and detest in a Moment the very same Persons sutably as they contribute to and jump with his Designs;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56781:4"/> This Man having a Book to present to one of his Patrons, he prevailed with his Bookseller to go with it, dawbing this Patron to him at a high rate, extolling his Wisdom, Benignity of Temper, and Generosity, you may be sure, with I know not how many other fine heroick Qualities: whereupon, away trooped the Bookseller with the Offring to the Lord; but coming back with disappointments in his Countenance, and telling Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> that he had delivered his Book, but that the Lord had returned no other Thanks than what consisted in Words, he began to curse and damn the Sordidness of his Patron, wish'd he had been in Hell when the Thought came into his Head of making him that Oblation: and thus continued he; vomiting out all the other Imprecations that can be urged against the most detestable of all Creatures, until the Bookseller, to divert this Torrent of Rage, shewed him some few Guineys which his Patron had sent him as a Present: and then to see the wonderful Effect that that Metal has upon Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Intellectuals; he immediately saw that good Lord again through quite different Opticks, and found in him a thousand more fine Qualities than he had ever done before; and in short, his Fancy dress'd him up as fine and as perfect as a Cherubin.</p>
            <p>But, to make an end with his tedious and dull Epistle, after he has, as he thinks, sufficiently burlesqued the Plot, he falls to insinuating, that it is so far improbable that the <hi>French</hi> King should be a Promoter of it, that he seems to hint there is great likelyhood of his turning Protestant, by reason of <hi>his fomenting the Protestants Rebellion in</hi> Hungary; <hi>or else perhaps a</hi> Turk, <hi>since he has brought the</hi> Grand Seignior <hi>into Christendom, and that perhaps not many hours Journey from the very Gates of</hi> Rome: <hi>And indeed, by his most Christian Majesty's Conduct, one would be apt to think that he was rather inclin'd</hi> to turn <hi>Musselman</hi> than a Protestant; for, otherwise he would treat the <hi>Hugunots</hi> after an other rate; for I do not hear if they be his Inclinations, that they are over fond of his manner of Courtship, and the Caresses they receive at present. After which, he says downright, That tho God <hi>knows there is not the least sign, appearance, or shadow of a Conspiracy, and the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusers of all this Poison into the unreasoning Multitude, are conscious, 'tis all rank For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gery, no matter for that; they know whom they have to deal with, the head-long Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bile of</hi> England, <hi>a People of that Constitution, that they fear nothing that they do, but all things that they hear: and those very Men that in visible Dangers, shall face the Mouths of Canons, yet at the apprehensions of Castles in the Air, Popery and Arbitrary Power, from the imaginary Thunder-bolt from that Quarter, shall start like Hinds: 'tis but winding that Horn, and they fall as flat before the Sound as the Walls of</hi> Jeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho; <hi>and nothing but breathing the Spirits of Rebellion into them can rouz 'em out of the Fright on't; and who at last are the great first Movers in all those national Enfla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mings. Truly those very Men that bawl'd lowdest for the Preservation of his Majesty's Person, against Plots and Popish Swords, are the numerical Persons that scandalize his Majesty with Popishly affected, to the withdrawing the Hearts of his Subjects, which are the greatest and strongest Guard against all Plotters Swords whatsoever.</hi> Thus in the first place he makes at one dash all the <hi>Commons</hi> assembled in Parliament to be guilty of Forgery, gives the Lye to all their Votes and their Petitions, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Addresses too that came flocking from all parts of <hi>England;</hi> and then bestows a very handsome Complement indeed upon all the whole Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalty of <hi>England,</hi> whom he makes a Visconary sort of Peeple, nay, worse than mere Brutes, acting blindly and without Consideration; and their Bravery, as he characterizes it, rather Stupidity than Courage. I know not what Stuff Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Relations be made of, but take my Word, the many brave Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mances of the <hi>English</hi> all over the World, have spoke as much Conduct as Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lantry: and I the more wonder he should bespatter so generous a People, in this manner, since he himself, by what I have ever heard, has none of that blind Boldness, unless it be in Writing; and then indeed, if he judges of all the rest of the <hi>Mobile</hi> by himself, he had some Reasons for bestowing upon them this Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter. And then as for accusing those Men <hi>who bawled lowdest for the Preservati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Majesty's Person against Plots and Popish Swords of being the numerical Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons that scandalized his Majesty with Popishly affected, to the withdrawing the Hearts
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56781:5"/> of his Subjects, which are his greatest and strongest Guard against all Plots and Swords whatsoever.</hi> Have not all the Votes of both Houses tended to the Preservation of his Majesty against Plots and Popish Swords; nay, have not all the Addresses of <hi>England</hi> been attended with offers of Lives and Fortunes for the Defence of his Majesty against Plots, as well <hi>Popish</hi> as others? And since all those who have bawled lowdest for the <hi>Preservation of his Majesty against Popish Swords are guilty of withdrawing the Hearts of his Subjects,</hi> do but read Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Character of a <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish</hi> Successor, and I fancy you will find him guilty of Treason.</p>
            <p>But, as he says, the Plot has been the Refuge and Sanctuary of all sorts of Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lains and Criminals. It has so indeed on all sides; and if any thing can lessen those who are stigmatized with the Name of <hi>Whiggs,</hi> it is the having suffered such Villains as <hi>Elkanah</hi> to herd amongst 'em: But as the <hi>Jesuits</hi> have crept into very Churches and Conventicles, the <hi>Whiggs</hi> could not at first discover nor purge away such kind of Vermine: but when they once found 'em out they fail'd not to clear the Party of them.</p>
            <p>And then Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> falls a telling us, that <hi>he dares now look Sense and Quality in the Face;</hi> intimating at the same time, that it is what the <hi>Whiggs</hi> dare not: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as 'tis well known, there be those who are called <hi>Whiggs</hi> who dare nose both Sense and Quality, and defie the Courage as well as the Arts and Machinations of their Enemies; tho indeed, if there be any of Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Leaven who shelter themselves and think to get Repute by herding amongst that Party, their own Conscience will without doubt check them in such manner, as only to appear, as he says, in <hi>Owl</hi> Light. But if they once come to be known for what they are, amongst the <hi>Whiggs,</hi> they will certainly banish 'em out of the Pales of <hi>Whigland,</hi> seeing they with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity make profession of entertaining no Commerce but with those who entirely abjure all Turbulency and Malignity whatsoever, and who make Loyalty, Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity, and Honesty, the rule of all their Actions, and not such as put on those Colours only to subscribe 'emselves a Patron's Humble Servant.</p>
            <p>Now as for his Narrative, I must own I do not understand the very first Line of it, <hi>In the Year</hi> 78. says he, <hi>It pleased those Powers that inspired them to raise.</hi> What, doth Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> mean that it <hi>pleased those Powers that inspired those Powere?</hi> There's Grammar indeed, but no Sense; but there's neither Grammar nor Sense in these Words, as Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> has set them down: but indeed, why should we be so unreasonable as to expect either from a Man who has no meaning in what he writes.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <note place="margin">Abselon and Achitophel. <hi>Second Part.</hi>
                  </note>Let him rail on, let his invective Muse</l>
               <l>Have four and twenty Letters to abuse;</l>
               <l>Which if he jumbles to one Line of Sense,</l>
               <l>Indite him of a Capital Offence.</l>
            </q>
            <p>After this Blunder at his first entrance, he as madly falls a ridiculing the Disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very of that horrid <hi>Popish</hi> Conspiracy even almost to Profanation, saying, <hi>P.</hi> 1. that <hi>Oats, Bedlow,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who by an ample Discovery (whether given us by the right or left hand of Providence, it matters not,</hi> according to Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Loyalty, the saving the King's Life, the preventing a Massacre of his Subjects, and the burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of his Cities, and the establishing of Separation and Idolatry in his Kingdoms, may as well prove a Curse as a Blessing, since it might as well come from <hi>the Left hand of Providence as the Right,</hi> but to proceed, <hi>it matters not) the Discoverers who came enlightned by Repentance and animated by Zeal, or something as active, to betray their old Collegues and Patrons, the Jesuits and Papists.</hi> Now that as <hi>Active</hi> I fancy had a great Ascendant over Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Narrative, and I believe a little Jesuitical Gold <hi>enlightned him with Repentance,</hi> and <hi>animated his Zeal.</hi> Well, we will for once suppose, Set a <hi>Thief</hi> to catch a Thief. Now, on he goes in the same Page; and that this Plot is more remarkable than all that <hi>Rome</hi> and <hi>Pope,</hi> Conclaves or Devils ever manag'd before, <hi>It has so many cross Windings, Turnings, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zes throughout, that whatever Wit, Prudence, or Conduct those great and politick Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of our Religion have ever been Masters of in former Intrigues, In this only Plot we
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56781:5"/> have a Cabal of such extravagant Fools and mad Men, as History affords no Parallel of.</hi> This, and some following Paragraphs are to insinuate how improbable a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it is that such <hi>Subtle Machia<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>elians</hi> as the <hi>Jesuits</hi> and their Adherents <hi>should take such indirect Measures and opposite means to obtain their great Ends.</hi> And therefore since such cunning undermining Foxes cannot be reasonably supposed to have fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en into such gross Over-fights and <hi>Infatuation,</hi> all the <hi>Popish</hi> Plot must by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence be a Sham, and falsly charged upon the Papists. But, with Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s leave, <hi>Rome,</hi> in the several Attempts it has made for the Pervertion, Reduction, and Apostacy of <hi>Great Brittain</hi> to the <hi>Popish</hi> Superstition and Power, having been still frustrated notwithstanding that its Designs were contrived with all the Art and Skill that humane Wit or devilish Policy could suggest, and therefore having incurred the just Resentment and Indignation of all those who have in Detestati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on its abominable Practices; I say, the frequent Disappointments of their Projects may be reasonably supposed to have made 'em use the Precaution that in case they should again prove abortive, and their Machinations be detected, that they might nevertheless appear in such Lights as to seem improbable to the World; and that then let the Issue be what it will it must turn to their Advantage; since if the Plot had taken Effect they had gain'd their main Point. But tho discovered and dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed, yet the puzzling Circumstances and the Improbability of the means as it might bring the Reality of it in question so it might also the Truth of its for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Conspiracies how manifest soever: and they from thence have an occasion of retorting 'em as Contrivances of their Enemies; and by that means purge 'em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves of the Scandal and <hi>Odium</hi> which they had justly brought upon their Church by such unchristian-like, nay, inhumane Undertakings. Thus the Instruments they made use of might many of them be as Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> says, mad Men: and who indeed but mad Men would be the Instruments and Ministers of such De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs. Were the Regicides of the two Kings of <hi>France</hi> otherwise than so? And how many Instances does not History afford us of those religious <hi>Enthusiasts,</hi> who have sacrificed their All for the promoting the Superstitions and Interests of their <hi>Mother Church.</hi> Besides, if Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> would but be pleased to look into the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>story of the Plot, I do not question but that he will find others besides extrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gant Fools and mad Men, in the list of the Conspirators: and as for the Members the <hi>Popish</hi> Cabals were compos'd of, there needs no great reading in Politicks to be informed that in many the greatest Undertakings the principal Contrivers and Promoters do not appear, only detatch one out among them who has the Secret of the Business, and who manages and sets all the other Wheels and Springs a go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Thus in Embassies, made up of several Collegues, seldom more than one has the Secret of the Embassy; and many times, Changes of State and of Religion, are often wrought and brought about by persons who seem to have abjured all Commerce with the World, and have devoted themselves to Gardens and to mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nastick, or at least a retired sort of Life. So that tho none of the Machiavels and Heroes of the Party had been brought to Light, yet must we therefore believe when their Ministers were discovered, that all was a Sham; tho these Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nisters having their Consciences seared, and their Mouths sealed with all that Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstition can invent, were bound upon pain of all the Curses which their false Religion made 'em think 'emselves liable to, not to reveal their Abettors: so that what Lunacy and Infatuation soever Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> may swell out in the management of the Conspiracy, yet I cannot find the Plan of it to be made of such Cobweb Lawn as he pretends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First then for their Killing the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This dire Ʋndertaking,</hi> says Mr. <hi>Settle, ironically</hi> upon so woeful a Subject, p. 1. of his Narrative, <hi>being the great Wheel that was to set the whole Machine a working. The Papists, by virtue of a Summons from Father</hi> Whitebread, <hi>had a general Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult at the White Horse Tavern in the</hi> Strand; at which were present Father <hi>Warren</hi> Rector of <hi>Liege,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Preston,</hi> Baronet; Father <hi>March,</hi> Rector of <hi>Ghent;</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Williams,</hi> Rector of <hi>Watten;</hi> Sir <hi>John warner,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Brett,</hi> Baronets; Father <hi>Pool, Edmond Nevil,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Who together with</hi> Dr. Oats, <hi>came over Sea upon the said Summons, and not the</hi> English <hi>Fathers at the said Tavern, in all to the number
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56781:6"/> of fifty Jesuits,</hi> on April the 24th. 78. <hi>Where, after long and serious Debates, the great Resolve of this general Consult was, that</hi> Pickering <hi>and</hi> Groves <hi>should go on in their Attempt</hi> to assassinate the King's Person; for which, the first should have thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand Masses said for the health of his Soul, and the other 1500. <hi>l.</hi> which Resolve they all consented and signed to, and Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> carried it from <hi>Consult</hi> to <hi>Consult,</hi> and <hi>Chamber to Chamber, to get all their Hands subscribed to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now this</hi> Pickering <hi>and</hi> Grove <hi>were Gunners that had followed the King for several Years for the same murthering Design, but ineffectually; Pickering,</hi> as <hi>Bedlow</hi> affirms, having had several fair Opportunities, but miscarried: one time the Flint of his Pistol was loose, another time there was no Powder in the Pan, and another time he had charged all with Bullets and no Powder; for which misdemeanour, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived twenty Lashes of Discipline. But his Comrade <hi>Groves</hi> for <hi>ought we know, never charged his Gun at all; for we read neither of his having any Opportunities, or hitting or missing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here is to be observ'd,</hi> pursues Mr. <hi>Settle, the great Depth and Wisdom of no less than fifty Politicians. These</hi> Popish <hi>Conspirators, that (as it appears) had been for several Years together at Pistoling the King, by the hands of these two Horoick Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thirsters, are at the Charge and Trouble of coming from several parts beyond Sea: and the great Result of that famous Assembly is, That these two aforesaid Wretches, a Brace of fumbling Fools, that had been so many Years aukwardly about it before, should still be continued and employed for the great Work of murdering the King, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out so much as the least Proposition of one wiser Head or better Work-man to come in for a Snack with them.</hi> Now I appeal to all Mankind, if they can find any thing of a Jest in so sad and so serious a Theam, as to be so merry upon, as we find our Author is: nay, on the contrary, would it not raise a Detestation in every true <hi>English-man</hi> and loyal Subject, for a Person, who can thus turn into ridicule an Attempt the most execrable that ever was hatched in Hell; and the very Thought whereof, tho suppose it but a Fiction, capable of creating a Terror and trembling in the most inhumane of <hi>Barbarians.</hi> Besides, where is the Improbability, Inco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence, or Contradiction, in this matter? <hi>Pickering</hi> attempted <hi>to kill him, but the Flint of his Pistol being loose he deferred it for another Opportunity.</hi> Might not this well enough happen by his Negligence, or rather, by God's Providence, who not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding all our Sins, yet thought not fit to deprive the World of a Prince, so much the Blessing and Darling of Mankind, and whose good Nature and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct have still found the means to temper and heal those Heats and Animosities which have produced such miserable Effects amongst our neighbour Princes and States; and which had almost brought his own People upon the brink of Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine.</p>
            <p>But this News came over to St. <hi>Omers</hi> in <hi>January,</hi> whereas the Consult for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the King was not till <hi>April.</hi> Still where's the Absurdity, <hi>Pickering</hi> attempted it, but was prevented through the Providence of God? Nevertheless, in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult in <hi>April</hi> following the King's Death was contrived, and they thought fit that their former Instruments should still continue to endeavour the committing that execrable Assassination until they had found fitter Tools for that purpose; perhaps lest if they were not encouraged but disobliged, they might, out of a just check of Conscience and Reluctance, come to reveal the Design. Ay but, says Sir <hi>Elkanah,</hi> Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> has contradicted himself in the Tryal of <hi>Pickering;</hi> for, <hi>not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the invincible</hi> Demonstration <hi>of</hi> January <hi>Pacquet, he more particularly ascertains at</hi> Pickering<hi>'s Tryal,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Try. pag. 24. Pag. 2.</note>
               <hi>the express time to be in</hi> March, <hi>being asked.</hi>
            </p>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Sir Ch. L.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Do you know any thing of</hi> Pickering<hi>'s doing Penance, and for what?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Oats.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes, my Lord, in the Month of</hi> March <hi>last, (for these Persons have followed the King several years) but he at that time had not look'd to the Flint of the Pistol, but it was loose, and he durst not venture to give Fire; he had a fair Opportunity as</hi> Whitebread <hi>said: and because he miss'd it through his own Negligence, he underwent Penance, and had twenty stroaks of Discipline.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <p>Well, says Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> upon this, <hi>Now can any thing in nature be more strange, than that</hi> Whitebread <hi>should send the</hi> St. Omer <hi>Fathers in</hi> January, <hi>a perfect Relation of a Crime not committed until</hi> March <hi>following.</hi> Now cannot I for the Heart of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56781:6"/> me see an <hi>Elliotisme</hi> in this whole matter; for might not <hi>Pickering</hi> commit the Crime in <hi>January,</hi> or before, and not suffer the Penance till <hi>March</hi> following: for the Question is only as to his doing of Penance, and the Answer is in <hi>March.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And <hi>to shew you,</hi> continues our Buffoon,<note place="margin">Pag. 3.</note>
               <hi>that this figurative way of speaking is an Elegance that the</hi> Doctor <hi>extreamly prides himself in, you shall have it from one end of the Plot to the other. For another Instance, at this very Consult, in his Narrative, and at</hi> Pickering's <hi>Tryal, the Assembly consisted of fifty</hi> Jesuits; <hi>but at</hi> Langhorn<hi>'s Tryal, because it was proved there never was a Room at the White Horse Tavern that could hold above a dozen People, then the aforesaid fifty, upon second Thoughts, were dwindled into eighteen or twenty, and those in several Rooms.</hi> Now says Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> in his Narrative, <hi>p.</hi> 28. <hi>That about nine or ten from</hi> St. Omers, <hi>met in</hi> London, <hi>in Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sult with</hi> Thomas Whitebread, <hi>Father</hi> Harcourt, senior, <hi>and Father</hi> Harcourt, ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nior, John Fenwicke, Basil Langworth, William Morgan, John Keines, <hi>Father</hi> Levill, <hi>Father</hi> Ireland, <hi>Father</hi> Blundall, Rich. Strange, <hi>Father</hi> Mico, <hi>Father</hi> Gray, <hi>and others, to the number of fifty</hi> Jesuits, <hi>met at the White Horse Tavern in the</hi> Strand, <hi>when they plotted their Designs for the Society, and ordered</hi> John Cary, <hi>who was also there, to go Procurator for</hi> Rome: <hi>at which Consult thus held in the Month of</hi> May, <hi>the Deponent was present to attend the Consulters, and delivered their Concerns from Company to Company: and then a little after, they left the White Horse, and divided themselves into several Clubs and Companies; some met at Mrs.</hi> Saunders <hi>House in</hi> Wild-street, <hi>others at Mrs.</hi> Fenwick<hi>'s at</hi> Ayre<hi>'s</hi> House <hi>in</hi> Drury-lane, <hi>others at Mr.</hi> Ireland<hi>'s in Russel-street near</hi> Covent-Garden, <hi>and in other places; all which, tho in several Companies, five or six in a Company, did contrive the Death of the King.</hi> Now he does not say that they were all in a Room; but on the contrary, in <hi>Langhorn</hi>'s Tryal, <hi>pag.</hi> 46. he says, they were divided into several Companies; and <hi>Langhorn,</hi> who had urged this matter for the lessening his Evidence, <hi>pag.</hi> 47. finding Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Oats.</hi>
               </note> justified, <hi>beggs that neither the Court nor the Jury would reflect up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him for pressing that point. And my Lord Chief Justice says in the same Page, You see how unfortunately it happens, the matter had not been much if it had been proved; but it's very unluckey these Persons should be here in Court by whom the other is contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted; it had been better it were never medled with; that she, namely</hi> Langhorn's <hi>Witness, should be so peremptory in what Standers by know to be false, makes this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction in one thing to give a Suspicion, that all your Witnesses may be false in all the rest.</hi> To which Sir <hi>C. Levins</hi> added in the same Page, <hi>Here is a Gentleman of good Quality that saith there have been fifty in a Room;</hi> neither does he say they were all at a time there: and as my Lord Chief Justice then observed, <hi>There might be twenty in the Morning, and some went away and others came in their Room, and so they might do in divers times of the day:</hi> and that this was so says Mr. <hi>Oats, they met there on the</hi> 26<seg rend="sup">th.</seg>
               <hi>Day at Night.</hi> And therefore methinks this is all plain to be understood, without seeming either Riddle or Mystery, even to as vulgar Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities as Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s.</p>
            <p>But then says our doughty Narrative-Writer, The <hi>Reader is humbly desired not to be puzled to imagine how Mr.</hi> Pickering <hi>should present a Gun between a Pistol and a Carbine twice at the King, which once for want of Prime, and another by being charged with all Bullets, would not go off, and yet not apprehended, or not so much as seen by any one of all the Kings Attendance, and that too in so publick and open a place as St.</hi> James's Park; <hi>a place where there is not so much as a Bramble or Bryar, or any one Covert throughout it, enough to shrowd a Pigmey, much less two Men-slayers, except<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the Osiers within the Canal (but those are moated round, and therefore inaccessi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: neither would I have the Reader surprized at Armies of Pilgrims and Legions of black Bills, and other miraculous Tools used in the Popish Service.</hi> Good Mr. <hi>Elkanah,</hi> unless thou hast the ill luck to have Readers as thick-scull'd as thy self, they will not be much puzled to imagine a Traitor sculking behind one of the great Trees, between which, with his Hat or Cloak, or twenty other things, he might have used for the hindering a Discovery, without having <hi>occasion for a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sty Cloak or needing to conjure up a Bush, that like</hi> Jonas <hi>Goad should have grown up in one day, and wither down the next.</hi> But poor Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> has this scurvy Quality to think every man as dull and short-sighted as himself; and because, forsooth, there be no Thorns nor
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56781:7"/> no Bryars, therefore every body, like him, must not see Wood for Tree.</p>
            <p>But now for the business of the Massacre: The <hi>Popish</hi> Army <hi>being to be fixed for striking immediately upon the King's falling, was consequently to be all listed and arm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the King's Life-time, and all</hi> incognito <hi>in a Protestant Kingdom, and upon ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving none but such notorious known Papists for the Commanders, it was morally impos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible to have drawn in any other Malecontents into the Conspiracy. Besides, the very Proposal of listing any of the Protestants, had been the way to have discovered the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spiracy, and ruin'd all; and therefore the whole Body of this Army must necessarily have consisted of all Papists. Well, where's the Wonder of all this.</hi> Is it not possible to list Armies in a <hi>Protestant</hi> Country, without being discovered until they them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves think convenient, being tongue-tyed, awed, and spirited by Superstition, Oaths, their own Biggotry, with the Insinuation and perpetual Spurrings on of their Priests? And pray, Why not this to be as well credited as to have a whole Protestant Army rendezvouz'd and encamp'd without so much as ever hearing of a Commission or Commission-Office?</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> and his <hi>Jesuits,</hi> Narrative, <hi>p.</hi> 4. were for <hi>doing the Work with</hi> Popish <hi>Generals and</hi> Popish <hi>Armies: But Mr.</hi> Dugdale <hi>is of another Mind, and he and his</hi> Jesuits <hi>were for quite another sort of Conduct. 'Tis true, he concurrs with Mr.</hi> Oats, <hi>That the King was to fall by as many private hands as the Doctor pleased; but then to subdue the rest of the Kingdom, a Massacre was to ensue.</hi> And because he and <hi>his Plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters were not altogether so strong as Mr.</hi> Oats's, <hi>and believed the Popish Party to be too small, and therefore too weak of themselves alone to go through Stitch with so great an Ʋndertaking, they had found this Expedient;</hi> viz. <hi>They had design'd (he tells you) to the Murder of the King upon the King-killing</hi> Presbyterians, <hi>and then to engage the</hi> Episcopal <hi>Party to rise with the Papists in revenge of the King's Blood, and cut the</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naticks <hi>Throats:</hi> and when with their help they had destroyed the Fanatical Party, and weakned the Kingdom by so universal a Blow, then they had decreed to turn their Swords all of a sudden against their Collegues the <hi>Episcopals.</hi> Now I must take the liberty to tell Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> that this seeming clas<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing to him in the Evidence of those two Persons, is both a proof of the reality of their Testimony, and that the Papists would leave no Stone unturn'd for the bringing about their Project. It shews that they did not confer Notes to jump in the same matter for the gaining the more credit to what they deliver'd, but that they impartially and ingeniously declared the Designs of the Papists so far as they had been made privy to them. It shews that the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> had several Ministers abroad for the carrying on its hellish Projects and Conspiracy; and that it had so many Machines a going, that so if the one failed the other might succeed and come to pass. And in fine, it shews that this Plot was no Contrivance of any <hi>Protestant</hi> or <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Party, for any private Designs of their own, as some both wickedly and unreasonably would fain suggest, since if it had, care would have been taken that the Evidence of the Discoverers should have been all of a piece. As <hi>Mr. Settle</hi> says, <hi>p.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now if</hi> Pickering <hi>had mended his hand, and killed the King, whom God defend, how must the Episcopal Party be possess'd it was done by a Presbyterian hand, seeing it was impossible the</hi> Jesuits <hi>should ever expect that a single Assassinate in such a place as</hi> St. James's Park, <hi>in the Face of the Court, and approaching so near as within Pistol shot, upon the Murther of the King, should ever escape seizing, either by the hands of the Nobility or his Majesty's Servants that always attended him.</hi> In Answer to which, Is it not reasonably to be supposed that <hi>Pickering</hi> having undertook that Assassi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate out of a motive of Religion, as a thing highly meritorious, since it so extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarily promoted the Interests of <hi>Mother Church,</hi> would, out of the same motive of Religion, charge the Presbyterian Protestants to be his Abetters, which un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly he was bound to do under the severest Penalties his Superstition and Bigottry might make him think himself lyable to. The supposing this will be no straining of the Point to any indifferent Reader, especially one should think to one of <hi>Mr. Settle</hi>'s Constitution, who has so boldly laid open in his <hi>Character of a Popish Successor,</hi> with what entire Submission and Devotion the Members of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> do deliver themselves up a Sacrifice for the promoting it's Causes and Interest. Besides, seeing the Papists were ever hovering about the King's
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56781:7"/> Person, upon the blow being given, might not they, out of a pretended officious Zeal, fall upon the Assassinate, mangle him in such manner as to render him al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together unknown again for the Person he was, and then lay at whose Door they pleased, either by real or forged Words, that execrable Murther. And upon this the Church of <hi>England</hi> men, out of a just Resentment and Indignation for the loss of their All, in so great, so divinely good a Prince, are reasonably to be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed, would revenge it with all the heat and all the vigour imaginable: and might not then they themselves have been given up as a Prey to their Enemies, and those Throats which escaped the ensuing <hi>Popish</hi> Massacre, have been cut and dispatched by the <hi>Popish</hi> Army: and by <hi>Mr. Settle</hi>'s leave, this is no unprecedent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Instance of <hi>Popish</hi> Barbarity; and not only <hi>Europe,</hi> but other parts of the World, have seen the hideous Scenes, and been the sad Theatres of their Inhumanity. In the <hi>West-Indies,</hi> with what unheard of Cruelty did they not butcher the Natives, hunting them like wild Beasts, and having them torn to pieces by their Dogs. In the Isles of <hi>St. Domingo,</hi> those that escaped their Dogs they put into the Mines, keeping the Women from the Men to hinder the Generation: and thus in seven Years time destroyed all the Natives of that populous Island. <hi>And therefore no Wonder that after they had mow'd down the Protestants of the Kingdom</hi> by so univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sal a Blow as a general Massacre, that they had an Army rais'd too for the destroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>even the very Gleanings of the Field.</hi> Their former Massacres, how general and how destructive soever, had not that effect they proposed to themselves by their not going through Stitch with em; they saw their Errors, and were resolved to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trieve 'em with a Vengeance: and now being grown expert in the Trade, nothing but <hi>Root</hi> and <hi>Branch</hi> would serve their Turn.</p>
            <p>Now as for <hi>Mr. Settle</hi>'s admiring what Need the Pope had in his long Bull, read by Dr. <hi>Oats</hi> in <hi>Blundel</hi>'s hands, after the Disposal of Bishopricks, Archbishopricks, <hi>&amp;c. for want of English-born Priests enough for all the Dignities of the Church of</hi> England, <hi>to decree such and such</hi> Spaniards, <hi>and other Forreigners, should supply that Want, and order such for reading Philosophy and Divinity in all great Towns and Colledges, and such and such to be employed in Catechizing and Preaching at the Altar:</hi> says <hi>Mr. Settle</hi> upon this, that it would have been all in vain, <hi>seeing three surviving Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies had been more than all the Families in</hi> England <hi>could have produced.</hi> Does <hi>Mr. Settle</hi> imagine that such a Country as <hi>England</hi> would have been long unhabit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, or does he not think that the Priests themselves out of their pious Inclination, for the encreasing the Lord's Flock, would do their best for the propagating Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration? They would, without doubt, Mr. <hi>Settle.</hi> We see they do it daily out of their Charity to Mankind: besides, the decoying 'em with the hopes of the fat Benefices of <hi>England,</hi> was the only means to make 'em bleed and contribute large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly towards the carrying on the Design.</p>
            <p>But, pursues <hi>Mr. Settle,</hi> p. 6. <hi>What if by a new turn of State</hi> Brittannus <hi>should be alive at last, and maugre this fatal and universal Doom, several thousands of these sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenced Hereticks should live many a fair Summers day after it:</hi> for <hi>Mr. Bedlow,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues he, <hi>says, that after the landing an Army of ten thousand Men from</hi> Flanders <hi>at</hi> Bridlington Bay, <hi>to surprize</hi> Hull <hi>Garrison, and the Lord</hi> Petre <hi>and</hi> Powis <hi>having another Army to march to</hi> Pembrookshire <hi>to meet a third Army of twenty or thirty thousand Men, who were to land at</hi> Milford Haven, <hi>being an Army compos'd of all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Men and Pilgrims from</hi> St. Jago <hi>in</hi> Spain; <hi>and whatever should happen that their Strength as they said might be sufficient, they had forty thousand Men (a fourth Army ready in</hi> London) <hi>besides those that would in the Alarum be posted at every Ale-house Door, to have killed the Souldiers as they came out of their Quarters;</hi> besides a sixth Army, continues <hi>Elkanah,</hi> of Mr. <hi>Oats</hi>'s from <hi>France,</hi> expresly to have been let in upon the King's Death. Now amongst all these formidable Armies the Edge of Mr. <hi>Dugdale</hi>'s Massacre is a little abated; for here, as <hi>Bedlow</hi> tells the House of Lords, <hi>after</hi> Conyers <hi>had killed the King,</hi> Keins <hi>the Duke of</hi> Monmouth, Prichard <hi>the Duke of</hi> Buckingham, <hi>Mr.</hi> Right <hi>my Lord</hi> Shaltsbury, <hi>Mr.</hi> O Neal <hi>my Lord</hi> Ossory, <hi>and one, whose Name he had forgotten, the Duke of</hi> Ormond; after all those Persons were killed, <hi>the Papists did not question the power of the rest of their Counsels but that they should out-do them; for they would give such great Pay, that all sorts of
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56781:8"/> Malecontents and People that depended on their Fortune, would be ready to serve them. All this performed,</hi> as he tells you afterwards, <hi>they designed to establish their Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment secure enough; for they intended utterly to extinguish all sorts of People that would not really be converted to the Church of</hi> Rome, <hi>and to prove it, persecute their nearest Relations that were obstinate.</hi> Now do not I see in all this matter any clashing be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Evidence of the Discoverers, nor between what they had before depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed; for as there be Garrison Towns, and those in the hands of <hi>Protestants,</hi> so there was need of Armies to reduce 'em in case they could not be surprized by other means: but in case they met with such Opposition at those places as might be a <hi>Remora</hi> to their Designs, their business was to invite all <hi>Malecontents</hi> and People that depend upon their Fortune as Souldiers are, who were to defend these Towns to forfeit their Trusts and be ready to serve them.</p>
            <p>But after Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> has thus prodigiously shewn the many and wonderful turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and windings of <hi>French Armies,</hi> &amp;c. p. 6. <hi>he falls to prove the Work was to have been done by no Armies at all;</hi> since, he says, it appears visibly, that the Design had been ripe for Execution many Years before the <hi>April</hi> Consult, seeing <hi>Pickering</hi> and <hi>Groves had been several Years dogging the King for the murthering purpose,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pag. 7.</note>
               <hi>by the</hi> Jesuits <hi>Order,</hi> and that the Commissions for the <hi>English</hi> Forces were not delivered till the Months of <hi>May, June, July, August,</hi> 78. Now may it not be reasonably supposed, that the Design of murdering the King being first midwived by the Jesuits, they thought that firing <hi>London</hi> and killing the King in the hurry, would so embroyl the Nation, as to make way for some such Foreign or Domestick Power as should absolutely depend on them, or at least second and maintain their Practises. But the Project coming to be canvass'd by the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> and es<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous'd by those of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain,</hi> they concluded more Precaution and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony was to be used in this Undertaking; they considered that the embroylng of a Nation, and the Death of a King, had been very far before from doing their Business, and therefore agreed to assist and second the pious, tho blind, Intention of the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> and for that purpose to have in readiness both within and from without such Forces,<note place="margin">Lords Journ. <hi>12</hi> day of Nov. <hi>78.</hi>
               </note> that <hi>whatsoever should happen, their Strength, as they said, might be sufficient.</hi> Thus that rough, weak, and ill-shapen Draught and Project of the Priests, was refined, strengthned, and polished by the practical and vigorous <hi>Matchiavellians</hi> of the Age, and such care taken that the Issue and Success must have been infallible, if God, out of his Mercy, had not been pleas'd to disappoint 'em by putting it into some of their Instruments Hearts to make a timely Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery.</p>
            <p>Nevertheless, let Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> not think to render the matter improbable, by hinting the <hi>Majority</hi> of the <hi>Protestants</hi> throughout the Kingdom to surpass by much the Papists, seeing the latter meant to decoy the Church of <hi>England-men</hi> into the Fact; which though they should not have effected, yet so unexpected a Surprise upon People unprepared, and at Dissention and Distrust among themselves by Persons martialized and used to Arms, as is well known the Papists had been, and who for a long while before had been making all things ready for the well managing of their Undertakings, they might well enough promise themselves Success, each not needing to be an <hi>Almanzor</hi> or a <hi>Mars,</hi> or have the Strength and Soul of a <hi>Hercules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>The <hi>Jesuits fired</hi> London, says E. Settle, <hi>with an Intention to kill the King in the Hurry, and massacre the Protestants upon't: and yet see the oddness of the Design; they laid</hi> London <hi>in Ashes, and yet were not at all provided to go through with the Work. And why, as the Doctor expresly tells us, they were not secure of the Duke, and for that the King was so industrious about the Fire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>that they could not find in their Hearts to do it; (a very odd Qualm of Pity in a Plotter,</hi> continues this Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain, <hi>and an extraordinary stop to a Conspiracy of almost a hundred Years growth.</hi> At this prophane rate does this Fellow ridicule the Effects of the Goodness of God, and turns his Blessings into a Subject of Scorn and Laughter; whereas there is nothing of Absurdity or Incoherence to give occasion to all this Mirth; for con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sidering the sadness of the time, a heavy War upon the Nation weakned by a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56781:8"/> dreadful Sickness: and now <hi>London,</hi> that may be called the very Soul of it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing consumed by Fire, if God too would have suffered them to have effected their Regicide, might not they have reasonably expected to batter down the Bulwark that had so long opposed the entrance of <hi>Popery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> is pleased to wonder that no inquiry has been made after the Booty which the <hi>Jesuits</hi> pillaged during that dreadful Conflagration.<note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 'Tis well known, that many besides the <hi>Jesuits</hi> enriched themselves by pilfering at that time, and why should not they who had prepared themselves for it and had posted themselves accordingly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Besides,</hi> says Mr. Settle, <hi>they made use of Fire-balls,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note>
               <hi>and those made of Sheeps-fatt, no more an Ingredient (to my Knowledge) for the Composition of a Fire-ball than for a Sack-Posset; and might be as honourably sworn into the one as the other.</hi> Now as for the Effects and Performances of these Fire-works, Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> has yet made, take my Word they have invalidated his Authority upon the point, and shewn that his Skill and Knowledge is as small and stinted in them as they are in his Narrative, Poems, and Plays.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Plot in <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>But there let us take our leave awhile,</hi> says Mr. Settle, <hi>of the Rebellion,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </note> &amp;c. <hi>in</hi> England, <hi>and see how the posture of Affairs stands in</hi> Ireland; <hi>for the doing of which, we can have no greater Light than from the Tryal of</hi> Oliver Plunket, <hi>late Titular Archbishop of</hi> Ireland; <hi>where indeed we find the whole</hi> Irish <hi>Plot so to Admiration made out, that even Infidelity it self must tremble at such undeniable Proofs, and unanswerable Demonstrations, and to the Confusion of</hi> Rome, <hi>all this undoubted Truth delivered by Oracles, sworn home by no less than the very Oaths of Members</hi> even of the Popish Clergy it self.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The whole Sum of which Conspiracy is as follows. Oliver Plunket</hi> was made Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate of <hi>Ireland</hi> by the Election of the King of <hi>France;</hi> and upon his Election, he made these Conditions with the King of <hi>France,</hi> to raise men to joyn with the <hi>French,</hi> to destroy the Protestant <hi>Religion,</hi> the said <hi>Plunket</hi> having engaged to get <hi>Dublin, London-derry,</hi> and all the Sea Ports into their own hands, to levy War and destroy the Protestant Religion, and that they should have the King of <hi>France</hi> to protect them, during Life; as <hi>Mac Keigh</hi> swears.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In all the</hi> Irish <hi>Plot,</hi> continues Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> p. 9. <hi>We have a Model of State-affairs extreamly different from those in the English Plot:</hi> as for Example, We find the <hi>French</hi> King not half so generous in carrying on the <hi>Catholick Cause</hi> in <hi>Ireland</hi> as in <hi>England:</hi> and good reason why, Mr. <hi>Settle;</hi> for I hope <hi>Ireland,</hi> how much improved soever, will not yet a while be put into Ballance with <hi>England,</hi> tho in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed another <hi>Popish</hi> Plot or two might do much in <hi>England;</hi> nicer and more vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous measures were to be taken: the <hi>Irish</hi> have been in Subjection time out of mind, and therefore could the easier digest a new Master since he brought along with him the Exercise of their own Religion; but the <hi>English</hi> are not of a Temper to brook the name of a Conquest, or the being made a Dependance to another Crown; all hands at work would be little enough to effect their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs upon them: but in <hi>Ireland</hi> they already had an instance how far a Mas<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sacre would go, tho the standing Forces there, and the steadiness of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did require considerable Aid and Assistance. And at the same time sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posing the <hi>French</hi> King the Abettor, and designing that Kingdom as a Morcel for his own use, it was not so unpolitick in him as Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> pretends, to drain the <hi>Irish</hi> of what he could, seeing that was the means of having them depend the more absolutely on his Will and Pleasure. Neither was the Conduct of the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> in this matter, such a Sollecisme at this time, if we consider, how prevalent the Counsels of the <hi>Jesuits</hi> have been of late Years, in the whole management of the Affairs of the House of <hi>Austria,</hi> even to their mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest Detriment and decay of that Family; so that this Undertaking and Conspi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy being a Brat of the <hi>Jesuits,</hi> and they having such an Influence over his <hi>Catholick Majesty</hi>'s Counsels, they may well enough be supposed to have obtain'd the mentioned Assistance and Succour, to be connived at and allowed of, since most of the Forces out of his Catholick Majesty's Dominions seem so many reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:56781:9"/> Volunteers, hapning to merit by such a pious Expedition; the rest might probably be raised and maintained out of the Priests Pockets, for the carrying on and promoting so holy a Cause, and only with the Connivance, as I said, of his Catholick Majesty.</p>
               <p>Thus the <hi>Spanish</hi> Army to be landed at <hi>Carlingford Haven,</hi> that other of thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty thousand <hi>Jago</hi> Pilgrims to land at <hi>Milford Haven,</hi> and the ten thousand <hi>Flandrians</hi> likewise to be landed at <hi>Bradlington Bay,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note> are to be looked upon, as I should think, as Forces, maintained by the common Purses of that Part of the Catholick Church in the King of <hi>Spain</hi>'s Dominion; who out of it's Zeal for so religious an Undertaking, should ferrit their Baggs. And what might the more invite them to do it, was, that this Money was only a kind of Venture which promised ten-fold Return, seeing they were to be setled in all the Parish-Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Benefices of the Kingdom. And the Priests have been found liberal enough in cases that redoun'd to their profit, and to the augmenting the Pale of the Church, whereas they have ever been found to be most damnable stingy and tenationary in all things that tended to the relief of the State.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>But the high and mighty King of</hi> France, <hi>says</hi> Mr. Settle, <hi>comes under the same Premunire of playing the Fool or mad-man, by attempting to bring a Navy into that very Port of all</hi> Ireland <hi>so notoriously known to carry scarce Water enough for a Fish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er-boat, much less a Man of War to ride in; besides passing through all the dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous</hi> Irish <hi>Seas,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>in the face of all the</hi> Irish <hi>Ports, and the Mouth of all the Kings Men of War, by so long and hazardous a Voyage, to give the three Kingdoms suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Alarum to prepare for their Opposition.</hi> Now tho the Popish Plot was disco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, were there not still Attempts made for the burning the Navy, was not the Massacre to be made and all the Ports secured, and might not the passing through those Seas be design'd for the keeping the three Kingdoms in Suspence of their Intention? and while they lack looks to themselves they might the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter effect their Designs upon that, and after landing might not the Fleet change its Port?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>10.</hi>
                  </note>Ay but, says Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> this foolish <hi>French</hi> King is at the Charge and Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>of manning out a Fleet to land an Army in</hi> Ireland: <hi>When, to the Shame of all ill Memories, both he and all his States-men had quite and clean forgotten they had landed one there already: for, does not the infallible Dr.</hi> Oates <hi>give us to know, in his Examination before the Parliament, in these very Words,</hi> That the <hi>French</hi> King had already landed a great Army in <hi>Ireland,</hi> being those Forces that left <hi>Messina;</hi> and it is to make 'em up 25000 men, which are to joyn with the <hi>Irish</hi> Papists in a second Massacre, to fire the City of <hi>Dublin,</hi> and destroy the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> and his Adherents: and this part of the Conspiracy was managed by <hi>Coleman,</hi> &amp;c. And why again not these 25000. as well as the Whiggs invisible Army? Why might not their Designs be disappointed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Discovery of the Plots, and they retire again, or forbear acting untill better strengthned and prepared for the bringing their Designs about. And this is not the first time the <hi>French</hi> King has been out in his Measures, and as Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> says, <hi>Humanum est errare.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But on goes blundering <hi>Elkanah p.</hi> 11. in this manner: <hi>Now it will not be amiss for our farther Light into this matter, to search the Mine from whence the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure comes to defray the Charges and to be expended to support so vast a Body of Cut-Throats. For example, What more unconscionable Disproportion could there be between the</hi> 15000 <hi>l. contracted for and no less than</hi> 1000 <hi>l. bid at first Word to Sir</hi> George Wakeman <hi>to poyson the King, and but that inconsiderable Trifle of but eighty Pounds given to the four</hi> Irish <hi>Russians, when most of them were Gentlemen of great or greater Quality and Fortune than Sir</hi> George: <hi>and the whole Sum of eighty Pound, no more than either of them would have valued spending in a Week; nay, and when more and above, Sir</hi> George Wakeman's <hi>Ʋndertaking had not the tenth part of the danger attending it, his Business being only the Legerdemain of slipping a Pill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary into the King's Brother so, and theirs to assassinate him in the face of open day.</hi> Well, these generous Assassinates perhaps desired nothing more than the Glory of the Fact, with what could furnish a Revel and a Treat after the Perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56781:9"/> of the Fact, or if they did, it might be the Employments and Estates of the massacred and assassinated Persons; and tho Sir <hi>George's Ʋndertaking had not the tenth part of their Danger attending it,</hi> yet being like most of his Profession, of a mercenary avaricious Temper, was resolved to make the best Market he could; whereas Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Estate and Quality Ruffian bravely undertook the thing, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of Gallantry than Interest, and left it to <hi>Groves</hi> and <hi>Bedlow,</hi> and such sort of beggarly Fellows, to make a Trade of and their Fortune of Assassination.</p>
               <p>Well but, continues Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> in his Narrative, <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>How close fisted soever the Jesuits were in the pityful Reward of twenty pound a Man to Persons of their Rank and Character, for killing the King; yet not long after, their bounteous Liberality was somewhat more open-handed, when they offered</hi> William Bedlow, <hi>alias</hi> Bedloe, <hi>ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally the Son of a Cobler, and at present a Runner of Errands, no less than the Sum of four thousand pound to hire him to kill Sir</hi> Edmundbury Godfrey, <hi>and that too when himself was but to be one of the four or six that were to do it; witness his Oath before the House of Lords. William Bedlow</hi> saith in his Oath, that this Examinant being treated with by Mr. <hi>Lephaire,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Watch,</hi> Jesuits, about the beginning of <hi>October</hi> last they offered him a Reward of four thousand Pound if he would be one of the four or six that should kill a Man that was a great Obstacle to their De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign <hi>(viz.</hi> Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey, as it proved afterwards; a very round Sum toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther if the other five were to be as well paid) But here the Reader is desired to take Notice of the most matchless Example in</hi> Mr. Bedlow <hi>that perhaps he has met with, instead of</hi> they have met <hi>with,</hi> if <hi>Mr. Settle</hi> will allow me to make it true Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar for him, <hi>and the vast and wonderful difference of some Mens Consciences, to use very Gentlemen to whom</hi> 500 l. <hi>was less in their Pockets than five pound in Mr.</hi> Bedlow's, <hi>could notwithstanding bite at</hi> 20 l. <hi>a Man to murder no less than a King, when on the contrary Mr.</hi> Bedloe <hi>refused</hi> 4000 <hi>l. to murder but a poor Justice of the Peace: for, as we have it in the aforesaid Oath, before the House of Lords, thus following, He this Deponent promised (viz.</hi> to <hi>Lephaire</hi> and <hi>Walsh</hi>) to be one to do it upon their gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving him notice: afterwards (<hi>viz.</hi> the Fryday before Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi> was missing) Mr. <hi>Lephaire</hi> met him this Deponent about four a Clock in <hi>Grays-Inn</hi> Walks, and appointed to meet him again the next day at the same place, about the same hour, to do that Business, that upon his taking the Sacrament to do it, he this Deponent should have the Money paid down; but he not liking the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sign, fail'd of meeting him, <hi>&amp;c. Is not this as I said before, a wonderful piece of self-Denial; but as wonderful as 'tis, here's the Fellow on't to come.</hi> Now you may be pleased to observe, that this wonderful piece of Self-denial which Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> so turns into Droll, is, that Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> should refuse 2000 <hi>l.</hi> in a Porteridge in carrying the dead Body into the Fields; such an attractive Sum, says Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> 'tis <hi>a Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle;</hi> truly it would be so if all men were of <hi>Mr. Settle</hi>'s Constitution, who perhaps is none of those squeamish'd and nice <hi>conscienced Men:</hi> but what if such a round Sum were offered him,<note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note> he would again undertake to write more <hi>Characters of a Popish Successor,</hi> tho he had not the Spur and Motive of his Spleen and Gall upon Justice being done against him. But <hi>Mr. Settle</hi> will be confoundedly mistaken if he judges of all men by himself; take my Word he'll hardly find his like: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let him not think it so very <hi>stupendious, That a Man privy to all the Popish De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>signs, one of their Commission-Officers, and consequently to be engaged in all the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant Bloodshed intended, (the King's only excepted) and that this Man should all of a sudden stugger at one poor Heretick's Dispatch, tho for</hi> 4000 l. <hi>Reward, or if that would not down,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Nar. pag. <hi>12.</hi>
                  </note>
                  <hi>to refuse</hi> 2000 l. <hi>and all but for the sixth part of the Luggage of one poor Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but to Primrose-Hill.</hi> Now many men, without it's being look'd upon as a Prodigy, have been known keen and eager upon undertaking a Design, and yet have faultered and drawn back when it came to Execution. The circumstances of Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi>'s Fortune might make him engage in the <hi>Popish Plot,</hi> but at the same time be glad to have the Drudgery of it performed by others; and tho such con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable Offers might tempt some of our late Narrative-Writers to engage in as base a Murder, yet the Generosity of some mens Tempers, how meanly soever born, is not to be bribed and wrought upon into an ill thing; or rather, the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, who had otherwise ordain'd, might make use of the Proposal of that very Act, to create a Reluctance in him, and so work him to a Discovery
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:56781:10"/> of that and the rest. And as for the <hi>vast difference</hi> between the Reward to be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for the Murder of the King and that of the four <hi>Ruffians,</hi> and that to Mr. <hi>Bedlow, but to murder a poor Justice of the Peace;</hi> it's manifest that the Papists were then in a strange Consternation upon the Discovery of their Conspiracy, which they knew not how to retrieve, but by stifling it in the Blood of the unfortunate Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man; and therefore cared not how lavish they were in their Offers for that Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose. And how improper soever that Assassination may seem to set their Affairs to right again, yet being at that time in such Trouble, seeing all their long and painful Projects upon the point of being quash'd: I say, all this alone, without the help of Heaven, was sufficient to confound their Intellectuals, and make 'em pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce nothing but abortive Resolutions.</p>
               <p>But then, says <hi>Mr. Settle,</hi> Narrative, <hi>p.</hi> 12. <hi>&amp; p.</hi> 13. that <hi>Bedlow</hi> and <hi>Prance</hi> disagree as to the Persons and other Circumstances of that horrid Murder. Now as for their disagreeing, <hi>Miles Prance</hi> owns to have been present and have had a hand in that Murder; Mr. <hi>Bedlow</hi> knows it only by a Relation; and by a Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion too of a thing which he had already refused to have a hand in, and at a time he was so much suspected by that Party, as that they made him take the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament twice a day for fear he should reveal. Now he being a suspected Person, and knowing the Murder to be committed by Papists, seeing they would have had him concern'd in it, and therefore in the Account they gave him thereof, might vary from the Truth, that so in case he should fail them, they might prove the thing could not happen according to his Testimony, and so baulk the Evidence: and a Story was of necessity to be flourish'd up for a Person whom they look'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as wavering, and in whom such a sign of Distrust as the not making him a Confident might create such a Distaste, as might prove of very ill Consequence. Now as for <hi>Mr. Settle</hi>'s pretended Improbability, <hi>p.</hi> 13. that the Assassinates should have notice of his Coming. Did not <hi>Hill</hi> on the twelfth of <hi>October</hi> go to Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundbury Godfrey</hi>'s House in the morning,<note place="margin">The History of the Popish Plot. p. <hi>4.</hi>
                  </note> and spoke to him, tho what was said not being known then? Taking his Leave, he went to <hi>Girald</hi> and <hi>Green,</hi> and with them staid hard by, waiting Sir <hi>Edmundbury Godfrey</hi>'s coming forth, which about ten or eleven a Clock he did, as be used to do, all alone; they dog'd him up and down (as they said) all that day, till about six or seven a Clock in the Evening; and then <hi>Green</hi> came to <hi>Prance</hi>'s House, and told him that they had set him, but did not name where, any further than by St. <hi>Clements,</hi> and that <hi>Prance</hi> must make all haste down to <hi>Summerset</hi> House, to the Water-Gate or Passage westward in the <hi>Strand,</hi> that goes into <hi>Summerset</hi> House, down to the Water-side; and there he should find <hi>Kelly</hi> and <hi>Berry,</hi> which he did, and they three waited there till about nine a Clock at Night; then <hi>Hill</hi> came in haste and told them he was coming, and that they must pretend a Quarrel, and he would fetch him in: <hi>Kelly</hi> and <hi>Berry</hi> did begin a seeming Quarrel; and just as Sir <hi>Edmundbury</hi> was passing by the Water Gate, <hi>Hill</hi> (who was acquainted with Sir <hi>Edmundbury,</hi> and Sir <hi>Edmundbury</hi> with him as having dealt with him formerly, steps out in a great deal of haste, and entreated <hi>him, for God's sake, to come in, for there were two Men a quarrelling, and he was afraid there should be Bloodshed;</hi> whereas his Presence, being a Magistrate, would presently quiet them. He refused at first; but the other was so importunate, that at last he consented, and <hi>Hill</hi> entred the Gate first, after him Sir <hi>Edmundbury,</hi> and just behind him followed <hi>Girald</hi> and <hi>Green;</hi> as soon as they were in <hi>Prance</hi> went up to the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-Gate to watch that no Body should come in that ways, and <hi>Berry</hi> was to secure the Stairs and Passage by the Chappel; but first he and <hi>Kelly,</hi> the pretended Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rellers, stood about the Rail by the Queens Stables, and as Sir <hi>Edmundbury</hi> went down towards 'em, <hi>Green</hi> suddenly threw a twisted Handkerchief about his Neck, and forthwith all four pull'd him down and throtled him, so as he could make no more noise: then they threw him behind the Rails, and gave him many violent Punch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es on the Breast with their Knees, and <hi>Green</hi> wrung his Neck almost round with all his force: <hi>Prance</hi> and <hi>Berry</hi> being come to them he was quite dead, they all help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to carry the Body into Dr. <hi>Godwin</hi>'s Lodgings, where the said <hi>Hill</hi> liv'd, who went before and opened the Door; when they were in they carry'd him up five or six Steps into a little Room on the right hand, and there left him that Night, and Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day all day and night.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:56781:10"/>
               <p>On <hi>Munday</hi> Night, <hi>Hill</hi> and some others of them removed him into a Room in the Upper Court, and <hi>Prance</hi> having a mind to see where they had laid him, they all went with a Dark-Lanthorn thither, and look'd on the Body; at which time Mr. <hi>Bedloe</hi> saw Mr. <hi>Prance</hi> and knew him again long afterwards.</p>
               <p>On <hi>Tuesday</hi> Night they carried him to another Room in the said Long-Entry over against Dr. <hi>Godwin</hi>'s Lodgings. And on <hi>Wednesday</hi> Night, being a removing it from thence, to the Room where it was at first, <hi>Prance</hi> happening to come upon them at that Instant they all ran away, and left the Body in the Entry, till he call'd to them, and then they came back, and laid it as at first in the little Room.</p>
               <p>Then that they might murther his Reputation as they had his Person, the two wicked Priests, <hi>Girald</hi> and <hi>Kelley;</hi> advis'd to carry him out into the Fields, and leave him there with his own Sword, in some obscure place, that he might be supposed to have murther'd himself; and therefore, his Money, Rings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were all to be left with him. This being agreed they resolved to carry him out at Night, and in Order thereunto, <hi>Hill</hi> procured a Sedan, into which about twelve of the Clock they put him, <hi>Prance</hi> and <hi>Girald</hi> carry'd him out at the great Gate, <hi>Berry</hi> the Porter opening the Door, who to avoid the Souldiers taking any notice, had invited them into his house, with Drink and Tobacco. Thus sometimes <hi>Girald</hi> and <hi>Prance,</hi> and sometimes <hi>Kel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Green</hi> carried him up towards <hi>Soho-Fields,</hi> hard by the <hi>Grecian</hi> Church, and there <hi>Hill</hi> attended with a Horse, and they set the Body up before him, and clapt the Sedan into a House as was building, there, but unfinish't, till they came back, and then <hi>Gerald</hi> the Priest said, <hi>I wish we had all such Rogues as secure as we have this, then</hi> Prance, because he was a House Keeper, returned home, and the other four went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with him, one leading the Horse, <hi>Hill</hi> riding and holding the Body, and the other two walking by.</p>
               <p>They carried him into an obscure place, about two Miles out of Town, towards <hi>Hamstead,</hi> near a place called <hi>Primrose-hill,</hi> and therein a Ditch they left his Body, <hi>Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rald</hi> having run Sir <hi>Edmund</hi>'s own Sword through him, and left it in him, but the Scabbard and his Gloves they laid on the Bank, at a small distance.</p>
               <p>And now with Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s leave, where's the absurdity in all this, where the two-fold way of Trappanning him, <hi>the two-fold fatal place, the two-fold murther, and the double set of Night-Walkers,</hi> but blundering is natural to <hi>Elkanah.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>And he can puzzle a Cause with as much ease,</l>
                  <l>As <hi>Hoggs</hi> eat Acorns, or tame <hi>Pidgeons</hi> Pease.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But pray ye let us see Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s most remarkable Observation, which is that none or few of all those numerous Letters and Pacquets, seen, carryed, read, and Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted by the several Discoverers should be couch'd in Cyphers, seeing they carried no less then the whole Sum of all their Consults in <hi>England,</hi> or elsewhere; and all the several Proposals and Methods, for Regicides, Massacres, Assassinations, and all the rest of their Villanies <hi>whatsoever.</hi> Now, might not 48 for the King, 66 for <hi>London,</hi> or Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-broth for the Parliament, with such like stuff, suffice so to blind and perplex the sence, as to conceal the meaning of it from all others than those who had the Key of those Cyphers, and might not those other Letters that had no Cypher be conveyed by such hands and means as they might rely on for the safety of the Delivery, and be Couch't in such terms though not in Cypher, as to seem to an unprepossessed Reader to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain nothing but indifferent Matters, though they, were stufft up with rank Treason. But why should we wonder that Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> is not acquainted with the Niceties of that kind, seeing he seems to have monopolized Ignorance.</p>
               <p>The next Subject of Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Admiration,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nar.</hi> p. 14.</note> is the Preaching Treason even to the School-Boys, and <hi>tho' all these Children so grown up as to understand Moralls as well as Letters, and yet not one of them from that day to this so unluky as to tell Tales out of School.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>May they not have, and do they not still teach their Morals and their Principles under other Disguises and Appearances than those of Jesuites? or those that are known for such may not they have such a superstitious awe upon their Scholars as to hinder them from babling?</p>
               <p>Another thing our Narrative-Spark carp's at in the Conduct of the <hi>Jesuites,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nar.</hi> p. 14.</note> in their design of Pensioning as one may say, <hi>The</hi> Members <hi>of the</hi> House of Commons, <hi>for the obtaining Liberty of Conscience, and of Collecting a round Sum of money for that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose when upon murthering the</hi> King, <hi>and subjecting the Nation by the Sword not only the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament had been dissolved, nay, and a</hi> Members <hi>Brains possibly as easily knock't out as</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:56781:11"/> Plow-jobbers, <hi>but more than all this, upon the</hi> Papal Empire's <hi>entring by Conquest, they might have put an end to the very Constitution,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Pag. 15.</note>
                  <hi>and being of Parliaments.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Well, might not that be done in the Intrim, in case any Obstacle should happen to the putting in Execution their main Plot, does it not appear throughout the whole Course of the Conspiracy that the Jesuites would leave no stone unturned for the bringing about their ends, that they would play at small game rather then stand out, and their sometimes pushing on a Toleration, and labouring at others to Prorogue and Dissolve Parliaments, were influenced according to the several Postures of their Affairs which might be sometimes ready for Execution, and then perhaps they are for <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogueing or Dissolving,</hi> or if something intervened thar constrained 'em to wait for a fitter Opportunity, for the giving the Signal for the Main blow, might not they then labour for a Toleration which must needs have contributed very much towards the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing their Projects.</p>
               <p>And as for mean Men being admitted into the Pallaces of Princes, if Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> was not altogether ignorant of History, he would call to mind a thousand Instances of the lowest Creatures having access to, nay, even made familiar with the greatest Persona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, when found fit Instruments for the carrying on their Designs.</p>
               <p>And as to what he says of the Doctors Memory, those Instances he gives thereof are not so prodigious and unexampled unless in People to whom nature has been so stingy and nigardly of all its gifts, as it has been to Mr. <hi>Settle.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But Mr. <hi>Settle wonders that the Jesuites should meet and consult for a fortnight together af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the first discovery, and yet not have the least him or notice of it.</hi> Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> must needs think that the Jesuits had a very prevalent interest at Court, if they could smoak a discovery that was made against themselves, it would be as if a Man being informed of design's to ruine him and his Family, should nevertheless send word to the Traytours, that they had better refer 'em till another opportunity, for that he had notice of their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices, this Example would be something extraordinary.</p>
               <p>And then for Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> not seizing any of those <hi>Letters, Pacquets, Memorials, Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sals, Commissions,</hi> that might have so coroborated his Discovery, as some he had only the sight of, so it would be madness to think he could take 'em away by force, as to those others he carried, he does not say but that he was accompanied by some of the Conspiracy; or if he was not, so manifest a proof of his Treachery, if one may call it so, to his Party, would cut of all means of his diving further into their Resolutions, and yet might be of little use, since perhaps, he could not have prov'd the hands: And as for that Courage of Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> which our <hi>Narrative Hero,</hi> is pleased so to droll upon, it shows that Mr. <hi>Oates</hi>'s whole care was even after the Discovery, not to give the <hi>Jesuites</hi> the least cause to suspect his being fallen off that so by a fair appearance he might insinuate and grow so well acquainted with the results of all their debates, even concerning the Discovery, as to reveal and prevent any hasty and fatal Resolutions, they might have taken thereupon; and though he began to give 'em some Umbrage, yet his persevering to come to 'em might reinstate him in their good Opinion, since they could not think him guilty of so much folly, as to venture himself among 'em, after having play'd them so foul a Pranck, especially knowing their Principles, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire their Dispatching, and hindring Criminals of that nature from doing further Mischief.</p>
               <p>Well, But <hi>Elkanah</hi> has found out a new Projection to sport upon, namely, that the Fathers of St. <hi>Omers,</hi> viz. <hi>Richard Ashley</hi> Rector, <hi>Edward Hall, Edward Nevill,</hi> and <hi>those</hi> of the <hi>English</hi> Seminary, did Write to <hi>Thomas Whitebread</hi> and <hi>other Fathers,</hi> in <hi>which was express't that it was now apparent that the</hi> Catholick Religion <hi>was to be brought in the same way that they had used for the destruction of the Father of this King, and as that could not be effected till much blood was spilt on both sides, so this must be effected by effusion of blood,</hi> &amp;c. Now that way Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> quotes Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> to affirm to be this.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Who besides the</hi> Popish Party, <hi>were the first Authors and Contrivers of the late Ʋnnatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral War, by their known Diabolical Arts of Inflaming Parties and Passions against each other, and of your Royal Fathers Sufferings and Barbarous usage, it was those that brought him to his end, and flourisht Swords and triumphed over his dead Body, whom they durst not approach when living.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, though the Issue of this Design was not according to the Project, that does not argue, they did not set it on foot, their business was to have fomented a Division, and so by weakning both Partys have destroyed both, they did not expect the one
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56781:11"/> would have succeeded to that degree it did, and so spoiled their Measures; and as for some of 'em venturing their Lives, Estates, and Freedoms, in the <hi>Royal Cause,</hi> I shall need only to urge that in the most barbarous Nations, there be some persons found, who are just, upright, honest and Loyal; besides, might not many of those who thus asserted the King's Cause do it with design as much as in them lay, to make the Ballance even, and might not those others of 'em who flourisht their Swords and Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphed over his dead Body, less Politick and more Zealous do it out of a particular Spleen they had to the head of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Church; and that they were the Fomen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of those unhappy-Troubles, notwithstanding all the Indulgence and Toleration they were allowed, I think it evident from their being ushered in by that dreadful <hi>Irish</hi> Massacre, and so adieu to Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> and his Narrative.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Reflections upon the <hi>POSTSCRIPT.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>AFter this Absurdity hunter had thus endeavoured to turn the Plot into <hi>Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cule,</hi> he continues in his Postscript Vile-flying the Proceedings of the Nation,<note place="margin">Series of all the Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the House of Peers. pag. 9.</note> and bespattering its Prudence with the most shameful of all Conducts.</p>
               <p>But in return to his Droll upon the 30000 <hi>Spanish</hi> Pilgrims, I shall need only to ask if we had not Forces in <hi>France</hi> during the War between that Crown and <hi>Spain,</hi> had we not forces too in the <hi>Low-Countries</hi> for its Relief against his Most Christian Majesty, and yet neither the Confederates or the <hi>French</hi> hereby provocated to an open Rupture.</p>
               <p>And how vain is what he would fain infer from the pretended great neglect in the Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> seeing the Lord Chancellor acquainted the House on the 26 of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1678. That the Duke of <hi>Ormond</hi> Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> being informed of the dangerous design there, against the Person of his Majesty; and his Government hath secured the Person of <hi>Peter Talbot</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and hath issued out a Proclamation against Priests and Jesuits, and hath taken examinations in the business, which his Lordship hath transmitted to his Majesty.</p>
               <p>And as for his Majestys Royal Person being expos'd, did not both Houses address to have the <hi>Militia</hi> raised for two and forty days.</p>
               <p>And was there not a strict Inquisition made after Fire-works; nay, and were not several Chests of Cartrages found in Mr. <hi>Choquee</hi>'s House in the <hi>Savoy;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Series of the House of Peers. pag. 45.</note> and did not the late Lord Chancellor publickly averr, at the Sentence of the Lord <hi>Stafford, That there hath been a general and Desperate Conspiracy of the</hi> Papists; <hi>and that the Death of the King, hath been all along one chief part of the Conspirators design, is now apparent beyond all possibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of doubting, what was the meaning of all those Treaties which were published about two years since, against the Oath of</hi> Allegiance, <hi>in a time when no Man dreamt of such a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troversy, what was the meaning of Father</hi> Coniers<hi>'s Sermon upon the same Subject, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly because there was a demonstration of Zeal, as they call it, intended against the Person of tht King, which the scruples arising from that</hi> Oath <hi>did somewhat hinder. To what pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose were alll the Correspondencies with Foreign Nations! The Collections of Money amongst the</hi> Fathers <hi>abroad and at home? What was the meaning of their governing themselves here by such Advices as came frequently from</hi> Paris <hi>and St.</hi> Omers? <hi>And how shall we expound that Letter which came from</hi> Ireland <hi>to assure the</hi> Fathers <hi>that all things were there in a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diness too, as soon as the Blow should be given? Does any Man now begin to doubt how</hi> London <hi>came to be burnt? Or by what ways and means poor Justice</hi> Godfrey <hi>fell? And is it not apparent by these Instances, that such is the</hi> Frantick Zeal <hi>of some</hi> Bigotted Papists; <hi>that they resolve, no means to attempt the</hi> Catholick Cause <hi>shall be be left unattempted though it be by</hi> Fire and Sword? <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Tryal. <hi>fol.</hi> 213.</p>
               <p>Now, <hi>As for Mr.</hi> Oates<hi>'s not being worth</hi> 12 d. <hi>and raised afterwards to</hi> 12 l. <hi>a Week,</hi> yet should be 700 worse for the Discovery of the Plot, where can this Contradiction-ferret find out the Absurdity of all this, might not Mr. <hi>Oates</hi> if the Plot had continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and he remained faithful to it, expected Promotions and rewards much more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderable than 700 of the <hi>Papists.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as for the Massacre and Rising,<note place="margin">Series of the House of Peers. pag. 139.</note> did not both Houses on the sixth of <hi>December</hi> 1678 make the following Address to his Majesty.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>We your Majesties most Loyal and Dutiful Subjects the Lords, Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons in Parliament assembled, having sufficient Testimony of the present danger, threatning your Majesties Sacred Person and Government from the pernicious Plots and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances of</hi> Popish Persons <hi>Ʋniversally spread over this your Majesties Kingdom, do most humbly beseech your Majesty for the safety of your own Person and security of the Publick Peace of your Kingdom, to Command and require your Majesties Sheriffs, Justices of the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:56781:12"/> Peace, Mayors, and other Magistrates within their several and respective Countreys, Citys, and Places in</hi> Engand, <hi>and</hi> Wales, <hi>to Apprehend, Disarm, and secure all</hi> Popish Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sants, <hi>and all others, who shall or may be justly suspected</hi> Papists, <hi>and them to oblige in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognizance with sufficient Bale to keep the Peace, and be of good behaviour, and in default thereof, them to Imprison, and to return, the Names of such Persons with their Recognizances, to the next general Sessions of the Peace, for their respective Limits to proceed thereupon ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Law.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons in Parliament assembled poor men, happen to clash in their Opinions with Mr. <hi>Settle,</hi> who charges 'em with the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehensions of imaginary Dangers, and for his part he defy's the Eloquence of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels to Convince any Rational man of the possibility of any thing like a Massacre, to be made by the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> hands in <hi>England.</hi> Nay, the Wag would fain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade us, that the Lords Spiritual and Temporal and Commons, be Dissenters, for he says one thing is strangely remarkable that none are so vehement against Popery and Plots as the Dissenters, for do not all their Votes ring with Conspiracies and Popish Plots; nay, one would think he had a mind to bring in Majesty it self into the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, for has not the King in several Gracious Speeches declared as much? Did he not say in that he made on the 21st of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1678, <hi>That he had been informed of a design a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst his Person by the Jesuits, that he would leave the matter to the Law, and in the mean time take as much care as he could to prevent all manner of practices by that sort of Men, and of others, who have been tampering in a high degree with Forreigners, and contriving how to Introduce</hi> Popery <hi>amongst us.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, notwithstanding all this and many more Instances and Authorities, for the believing a Popish Plot, Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> says, that all <hi>this is but setting up Shadows und Chimera's like so many</hi> Ignes fatul, <hi>to mislead deluded Ignorance into Distraction and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, whilst the great Knaves trale the Carrion, and the little Fools hunt after it:</hi> Now dare not I for the Heart of me, imagine who Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> means by those <hi>Great Knaves</hi> and <hi>Little Fools,</hi> but must needs say, that I think this Salley of his is the boldest piece of Extravagance and of Madness I have yet met with in a Person of Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitution. But seeing Poets of Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Rank are like to starve since nothing now will pass the Test but what is reasonably good, since Belly Timber must be had, and that Hunger is one of the greatest Incentives to Courage, why shoald we think it so prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious an Attempt in him as to Attack and Stab the Evidence that has been given in against Popery, though under the Umbrage of Kings, Lords, and Commons, Mr. <hi>Settle</hi> is perhaps of the humour of <hi>Lott</hi>'s Wife, who upon a Pinch would even Curse God, if that would give any ease, nay, would <hi>Renegadoe</hi> it every day rather than stand the Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries of a Dun and the Importunities of a sharp set Stomach; but allow him to be no such <hi>Protheus</hi> sort of Animal, and that his Spleen and Venome still continues against the Papists and their Abbeters, may he not have written his Narrativr to shame them and their Cause by so scurrilous a Vindicator and Author. But to draw him more to the Life, our Narrative-jobber may be said to be like those Persons who having for a while been reclaimed from their lewd Course of Life, yet growing weary of that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>straint and giving way to the Viciousness of their Temper burst out of the Arms of their Charactable Redeemers plunge then again head long into all manner of wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness, and like the Dog return to his Vomit.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="note">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>SOme Remarks being come out in answer to Mr. <hi>Settle</hi>'s Narrative, whilst the last two Sheets of this were in the Press. The <hi>Reader</hi> is desired, not to be surprized, that something in these Reflections do jump with that Ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Author's Observations.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>